Guide to the Joseph Bendich Collection MSS.534
Fales Library and Special Collections
Joseph Bendich Collection
circa 1940-2005
1970-1999
Fales Library and Special Collections
Bendich, Joseph
MSS.534
3.5 linear feet in 3 record cartons and 1 small box
Joseph Bendich (1917-2005) was a amateur videographer and machinist who manufactured parts for lunar landing modules. This collection consists of film equipment and other items collected by Bendich for private film viewings. Materials include a Super 8mm movie projector, a Super 8mm movie light, a Keystone Super 8mm camera, a camera case, a photo lamp, a Revere film splicer, and splice tape instructions. The collection also includes three Super 8mm pornographic films: Jocks and Socks (Golden Girls), Sex Ed Tutor (Diamond Collection), and Reluctant Virgin Pt II (San Francisco Series). The artifacts in this collection are emblematic of the types of film equipment used by many Super 8mm auteurs of the late 20th century, including Nelson Sullivan, Chris Kraus, and David Wojnarowicz. This collection documents the ways in which pornography - particularly stag film - was circulated and watched during this time period.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of film equipment and other items collected by Joseph Bendich for private film viewings. Materials include a Super 8mm movie projector, a Super8mm movie light, a Keystone Super 8mm camera, a camera case, a photo lamp, a Revere film splicer, and splice tape instructions. The collection also includes three Super 8mm pornographic films: Jocks and Socks (Golden Girls), Sex Ed Tutor (Diamond Collection), and Reluctant Virgin Pt II (San Francisco Series). The artifacts in this collection are emblematic of the types of film equipment used by many Super 8mm auteurs of the late 20th century, including Nelson Sullivan, Chris Kraus, and David Wojnarowicz. This collection documents the ways in which pornography - particularly stag film - was circulated and watched during this time period.
Biographical Note
Joseph Bendich (1917-2005) was a amateur videographer and machinist who manufactured parts for lunar landing modules. He also owned a French laundry service.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Debra Schiff in October 2016; the accession number associated with this gift is 2018.074.
Film projection systems; Cameras (photographic equipment); Pornography.; Pornographic films.; Pornography -- Social aspects.; Sex in mass media
- Keystone XL 500 Super 8mm Camera, circa 1970-1979 (Box 1)
- Camera Case, circa 1970-1979 (Box 1)
- Wiko A/V Photo Lamp, circa 1960-1979 (Box 1)
- Jocks and Socks, circa 1965-1979 (Box 1)
- Sex Ed Tutor, circa 1960-1979 (Box 1)
- Reluctant Virgin Pt II, circa 1960-1979 (Box 1)
- Top Mount Movie Light, circa 1960-1979 (Box 2)
- Baia Super 8mm Editor/Viewer, circa 1960-1979 (Box 2)
- Bell and Howell Model 356 Autoload Super 8 Movie Projector, circa 1960-1979 (Box 3)
- Baia Splice Tape Instructions, circa 1960-1979 (Box 3)
- Receipts, circa 1960-1979 (Box 3)
- Revere Splicer, circa 1940s (Box 4)